<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A representation from His Excellencie S. Thomas Fairfax and the army under his command humbly tendered to the Parliament concerning the just and fundamentall rights and liberties of themselves and the kingdome, with some humble proposals and desires in order thereunto, and for settling the peace of the kingdome.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28984</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10789104</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10789104</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45897</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40571)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45897)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1383:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A representation from His Excellencie S. Thomas Fairfax and the army under his command humbly tendered to the Parliament concerning the just and fundamentall rights and liberties of themselves and the kingdome, with some humble proposals and desires in order thereunto, and for settling the peace of the kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 [i.e. 16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"St. Albanes, June 14, 1647. By the appointment of His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, with the officers and souldiery under his command. J. Rushworth, Secretary."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45897:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45897:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REPRESENTATION FROM HIS EXCELLENCIE S<hi rend="sub">r</hi>. <hi>THOMAS FAIRFAX,</hi> And the Army under his command, Humbly tendered to the PARLIAMENT: Concerning the juſt and fundamentall Rights and Liberties of themſelves and the Kingdome, with ſome humble propoſals and deſires in order thereunto, and for ſettling the Peace of the Kingdome.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Albanes,</hi> 
                              <date>June 14. 1647.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>By the appointment of his Excellency Sir <hi>THOMAS FAIRFAX,</hi> with the Officers and Souldiery under his Command.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>J. Ruſhworth, <hi>Secretary.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE:</hi> Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Univerſitie.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45897:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat we may no longer be the diſ-ſatisfaction of our friends, the ſubject of our enemies malice (to work jealouſies and miſrepreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations upon,) and the ſuſpicion, if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtoniſhment, of many in the Kingdome, in our late or preſent tranſactions and conduct of buſineſſe; we ſhall in all faithfulneſſe and clearneſſe profeſſe and declare unto you, thoſe things which have of late protracted and hindered our disbanding; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent grievances which poſſeſſe our Army, and are yet unreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died; with our deſires as to the complete ſettlement of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and peace of the Kingdome, which is that bleſſing of God, then which, of all worldly things nothing is more dear unto us, or more precious in our thoughts, we having hitherto thought all our preſent enjoyments (whether of life, or livelihood, or neareſt relations) a price but ſufficient to the purchaſe of ſo rich a bleſſing; that we and all the free-born people of this Nation, may ſit down in quiet under our vines, and under the glorious adminiſtration of Juſtice and righteouſneſſe, and in full poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe fundamentall rights and liberties, without which we can have little hopes (as to humane conſiderations) to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy either any comfort of life, or ſo much as life it ſelf, but at the pleaſures of ſome men, ruling merely according to will and power. It cannot be unknown what hath paſſed betwixt the Parliament and the Army, as to the ſervice of Ireland; By all w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> together with the late proceedings againſt the Army, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their petitions and grievances, all men may judge what hath hindered the Army from a ready ingagement in that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45897:2"/>
and (without further account or apology, as to that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) then what thoſe paſſages and proceedings themſelves (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready made publick) do afford; We do appeal to all men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe courſes to which the Parliament hath (by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and practice of ſome) been drawn, have rationally tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to induce a chearfull and unanimous undertaking of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as to that ſervice, or rather to break and pull the Army in pieces, with diſcontents and diſhonour; and to put ſuch diſ-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations and provocations upon it, as might drive it into diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and indeed diſcourage both this Army and other ſouldiers, from any further ingagement in the Parliament ſervice. And we wiſh all men would, with us, upon the whole carriage ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider, Whether in the intentions of thoſe who have by falſe informations and miſ-repreſentations, put the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon ſuch wayes, the timely and effectuall relief of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſeem really to have been intended; or rather (with the breaking and disbanding of this Army) to draw together, or raiſe ſuch other forces, and of ſuch a temper, as might ſerve to ſome deſperate and deſtructive deſignes in England: For which (beſides the probable ſuſpicions from their carriage of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe) we have before-hand in the tranſ-action thereof, had more then hints of ſuch a deſigne, by clear expreſſions to that purpoſe from many of thoſe Officers of the Army, that have been perſwaded, and appeared moſt forward to engage for Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land on the terms propoſed: And that ſuch a deſigne hath all along been driven, ſeems now too evident, by the preſent diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of thoſe forces that have been engaged (as for Ireland) by the endeavours of ſome, to gain a power from the Parliament of ordering the ſame for ſome ſervice in England, and by the private liſtings of men for ſervice here, without any publick au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament; and all this by the ſame perſons who have all along appeared moſt active and violent in the late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt the Army.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45897:3"/>As to the juſt diſcontents and diſ-ſatisfactions of the Army, in relation to their grievances, and their non-compliance to the late Orders for ſudden disbanding by piece-meal, before more full and equall ſatisfaction were given to the whole; We deſire you to look back to the papers already publiſhed of the grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces themſelves, the Narrative of the Officers, and to the later papers from the Generall Councel of Warre at <hi>Bury,</hi> and from the late Generall Rendezvouz laſt week near <hi>Newmarket:</hi> And (we think) the Parliaments late reſuming the Conſideration of thoſe things (as to a further ſatisfaction) doth much juſtifie the deſires and proceedings of the Army, in thoſe paſt particulars hitherto.</p>
            <p>And though (had we upon our firſt addreſſes) for our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted rights and dues, found a free and candid reception, with a juſt conſideration and reaſonable ſatisfaction; or at leaſt an ingenuous anſwer therein, we ſhould have been eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to have abated, or forborn much of our dues, and not to have inquired into or conſidered (ſo far as we have) either the poſſibilities there are for more preſent ſatisfaction of Arrears, or the credit of future ſecurities propoſed; Yet ſince upon thoſe former addreſſes, we have found ſuch unworthy dealing, as in the ſaid papers is ſet forth; and thoſe additionall (though hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to but partiall) ſatisfactions coming ſo hardly as they have; We find no obliging reaſons, in the leaſt, to decline or recede from what's our due, but rather ſtill to adhere unto our deſires, of full and equall ſatisfaction, in all the things mentioned in the aforeſaid papers, not onely in behalf of our ſelves and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, but alſo of the whole ſouldiery throughout the Kingdome, who have concurred or ſhall concurre with us in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and to all our former deſires. As ſouldiers we cannot but adde this (wherein we find our ſelves ſo nearly concerned in point of juſtice and reputation) that more care, and a ſtricter courſe may be taken, for making good all Articles granted upon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45897:3"/>
ſurrenders, according to the true intent and meaning of them; as alſo for remedy and reparation in caſe of any Breach (and this) without thoſe delayes which divers have found as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall, or more, then if they had been totally denied the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them.</p>
            <p>Nor will it now (we hope) ſeem ſtrange or unſeaſonable to rationall and honeſt men, who conſider the conſequence of our preſent caſe to their own and the Kingdomes, as well as our future concernments in point of right, freedome, peace and ſafety, if (from a deep ſenſe of the high conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of our preſent caſe, both to our ſelves in future and all other people) we ſhall before disbanding proceed in our own and the Kingdomes behalf, to propound and plead for ſome proviſion for our and the Kingdomes ſatisfaction, and future ſecurity in relation to thoſe things, eſpecially conſidering that we were not a mere mercenary Army, hired to ſerve any Arbitrary power of a ſtate, but called forth, and conjured by the ſeverall Declarations of Parliament to the defence of our own and the peoples juſt rights and liberties, and ſo we took up Arms in judgement and conſcience to thoſe ends, and have ſo continued them, and are reſolved, according to your firſt juſt deſires in your Declarations, and ſuch principles as we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from your frequent informations, and our own common ſenſe, concerning theſe our fundamentall rights and liberties, to aſſert and vindicate the juſt power and rights of this Kingdome in Parliaments, for thoſe common ends premiſed, againſt all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power, violence and oppreſſion and all particular parties and intereſts whatſoever, the ſaid Declarations ſtill directing us to the Equitable ſenſe of all Laws and Conſtitutions, as diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with the very letter of the ſame, and being ſupreme to it, when the ſafety and preſervation of all is concerned, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us that all authority is fundamentally ſeated in the office, and but miniſterially in the perſons, neither do or will theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45897:4"/>
our proceedings (as we are fully and in conſcience perſwaded) amount to any thing unwarrantable before God and men, being thus far much ſhort of the common proceedings in other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to things of an higher nature then we have yet appeared to: And we cannot but be ſenſible of the great complaints that have been made to us generally in the Kingdome from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, where we march, of Arbitrarineſſe and Injuſtice to their great and inſupportable oppreſſions.</p>
            <p>And truely ſuch Kingdomes as have according both to the law of Nature and Nations, appeared to the Vindications and defences of their juſt rights and liberties, have proceeded much higher: as our Brethren of Scotland, who in the firſt beginning of theſe late differences, aſſociated in Covenant from the very ſame principles and grounds, having no viſible form either of Parliament or King to countenance them: And as they were therein juſtified, and protected by their Owne, and this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome alſo, ſo we juſtly ſhall expect to be.</p>
            <p>We need not mention the States of the Netherlands, the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals, and others, all proceeding upon the ſame Principles of Right and Freedome: And accordingly the Parliament hath declared it no reſiſtance of Magiſtracy, to ſide with the juſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Law, Nature, and Nations; being that Law, upon which we have aſſiſted You. And that the Souldiery may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully hold the hands of that Generall who will turn his Cannon againſt his Army, on purpoſe to deſtroy them: The Sea-men the hands of that Pylot, who wilfully runs the Ship upon the Rock, (as our Brethren of Scotland argued:) And ſuch were the proceedings of our Anceſtours of famous memory, to the purchaſing of ſuch Rights and Liberties, as they have enjoyed through the price of their Bloud, and we both by that and the latter Bloud of our dear Friends, and fellow Souldiers, with the hazard of our own, do now lay claim unto.</p>
            <p>Nor is that ſupreme end (the Glory of God) wanting in theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45897:4"/>
caſes to ſet a price upon all ſuch proceedings of righteouſneſſe, and Juſtice, it being one witneſſe of God in the world, to carry on a Teſtimony againſt the injuſtice, and unrighteouſneſſe of men, and againſt the miſcarriages of Government: when cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or declining from their primitive and originall glory.</p>
            <p>Theſe things we mention but to compare proceedings, and to ſhew, that we are ſo much the more juſtifiable and warranted in what we do, by how much we come ſhort of that height and meaſure of proceedings which the people in free Kingdoms and Nations, have formerly practiſed.</p>
            <p>Now having thus far cleared our way in this buſineſſe, we ſhall proceed to propound ſuch things as we do humbly deſire, for the ſettling and ſecuring of our own, and the Kingdomes Right, Freedome, Peace, and ſafety, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">I. That the Houſes may be ſpeedily purged of ſuch Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; as for their delinquency, or for corruption, or abuſe to the State, or undue election, ought not to ſit there; whereof the late elections in Cornwall, Wales, and other parts of the Kingdome, afford too many examples to the great prejudice of the peoples freedome in the ſaid Election.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That thoſe perſons who have in the late unjuſt, and high proceedings againſt the Army, appeared to have the will, the confidence, credit, and power to abuſe the Parliament, and the Army, and indanger the Kingdome in carrying on ſuch things againſt us while an Army; may be ſome way ſpeedily diſabled from doing the like or worſe to us, (when disbanded, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed, and in the condition of private men) or to other the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of England, in the ſame condition with us, and that (for that purpoſe) the ſame perſons may not continue in the ſame power, (eſpecially) as Our and the Kingdomes judges in the higheſt Truſt, but may be made incapable thereof for future.</p>
            <p>And if it be queſtioned who thoſe are, we thought not fit particularly to name them in this our repreſentation to you, but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45897:5"/>
ſhall very ſpeedily give in their names, and before long, ſhall offer what we have to ſay againſt them to your Commiſſioners, wherein we hope ſo to carry our ſelves, as that the world ſhall ſee we aim at nothing of private Revenge, or Animoſity, but that Juſtice may have a free courſe, and the Kingdome be eaſed; (at leaſt) by diſinabling ſuch men from places of Judicature, who deſiring to advantage &amp; ſet up themſelves and their party, in a generall confuſion have endeavoured to put the Kingdome into a new flame of warre, then which nothing is more abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent unto us.</p>
            <p>But becauſe neither the granting of this alone would be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſecure our Own, and the Kingdomes Rights, Liberties, and Safety, either for the preſent Age, or Poſterity; nor would the propoſall of this ſingly be free from the ſcandall and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Faction, or deſigne onely to ſuppreſſe one party (under the notion of unjuſt, or oppreſſive:) that we may advance ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which may be imagined more our own; We therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that indeed we cannot but wiſh that ſuch men, and ſuch onely might be preferred to the great power and truſt of the Common-wealth, as are approved at leaſt for morall righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; and of ſuch we cannot but in our wiſhes preferre thoſe that appear acted thereunto by a principle of Conſcience and Religion in them, and accordingly we do and ever ſhall bleſſe God for thoſe many Worthies, who through his providence have been choſen into this Parliament: and to ſuch mens endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours (under God) we cannot but attribute that vindication in part of the Peoples Rights, and Liberties; and thoſe beginnings of a juſt Reformation, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the proceedings of the beginnings of this Parliament appeared to have driven at, &amp; tended to, though of late obſtructed or rather diverted to other ends and intereſts by the prevailing of other Perſons, of other Principles and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. But we are ſo far from deſigning or complying to have any abſolute arbitrary power, fixed or ſetled for continuance in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45897:5"/>
any perſons whatſoever; as that if we might be ſure to obtain it, we cannot wiſh to have it ſo in the perſons of any who we might beſt confide in, or who ſhould appear moſt of our own opinions or principles, or whom we might have moſt perſonall aſſurance of, or intereſt in, but we do, and ſhall much rather wiſh, that the authority of this Kingdome in the Parliaments rightly conſtituted, free, equally, and ſucceſſively choſen, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to its originall intention, may ever ſtand and have its courſe; and therefore we ſhall apply our deſires chiefly to ſuch things, as (by having Parliaments ſettled in ſuch a right co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution) may give more hopes of Juſtice, and Righteouſneſſe, to flow down equally to all in that its ancient chanell, without any overture, tending either to overthrow that foundation either of order or government in this Kingdome, or to ingroſſe that power for perpetuity, into the hands of any particular perſon, or party whatſoever. And for that purpoſe, though as we have found it doubted by many men (minding ſincerely the publick good) but weighing ſo fully all conſequences of things, it may and is not unlike to prove, that upon the end of this Parliament and election of a new, the conſtitution of ſucceeding Parliaments (as to the perſons elected) may prove for the worſe many waies, yet ſince neither in the purging of this preſent Parliament, nor in election of new, we can promiſe to our ſelves an aſſurance of Juſtice, or other poſitive good from the hands of men, but thoſe that appear for preſent moſt righteous, and moſt for common good, (having an unlimited power fixed in them during life or pleaſure) in time may become corrupt, or ſettle into parties or factions; or on the other ſide in caſe of new elections thoſe that ſhould ſo ſucceed, may prove as bad or worſe then the former:</p>
            <p>We therefore humbly conceive that (of two inconveniences the leſſe being to be choſen) the main thing to be intended in the caſe (and beyond which humane providence cannot reach, as to any aſſurance of poſitive goods) ſeems to be this, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:45897:6"/>
to provide that however unjuſt and corrupt perſons of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in preſent or future, may prove, or whatever it be they may do to particular parties, or to the whole in particular things during their reſpective terms or periods, yet they ſhall not have the temptation or advantage of an unlimited power fixed in them during their own pleaſure, whereby to perpetuate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and oppreſſion upon any, without end or remedy; or to advance and uphold any one particular partie, faction, or inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt whatſoever, to the oppreſſion or prejudice of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the enſlaving of the Kingdome unto all poſterity, but that the people may have an equall hope or poſſibility, if they have an ill choice at one time, to mend it in another, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may be in a capacity to taſte of ſubjection as well as rule, and may be ſo inclined to conſider of other mens caſes, as what may come to be their own. This we ſpeak of in relation to the Houſe of Commons, as being intruſted on the peoples behalf, for their intereſt in that great and ſupreme power of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, (<hi>viZ.</hi> the legiſlative power, with the power of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Judgements) which being in its own nature ſo arbitrary, and in a manner unlimited, unleſſe in point of time, is moſt unfit and dangerous as to the peoples intereſt, to be fixt in the perſons of the ſame now during life or their own pleaſures, neither by the originall conſtitution of this State, was it, or ought it to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo (nor doth it, where ever it is, and continues ſo) render that ſtate any better then a mere tyranny, or the people ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to it any better then vaſſals: but in all ſtates where there is any face of common freedome, and particularly in this ſtate of England (as is moſt evident both by many poſitive lawes and ancient conſtant cuſtome) the people have a right to new and ſucceſſive elections, unto that great and ſupreme truſt, at certain periods of time, which is ſo eſſentiall and fundamentall to their freedome, as it cannot or ought not be denyed them this, without which the Houſe of Commons is of very little
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45897:6"/>
concernment to the intereſt of the commons of England, yet in this we would not be miſunderſtood to blame thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of both Houſes, whoſe zeal to vindicate the liberties of this nation, cld procure that Act for continuance of Parliament, whereby it was ſecured from being diſſolved at the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as former Parliaments have been: and reduced to ſuch a certainty, as might enable them the better to aſſiſt and vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the liberties of this Nation (immediately before ſo highly invaded, and then alſo ſo much endangered) and this we take to be the principall ends and grounds, for which in that exigency of time and affairs it was procured, and to which we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it hath happily been made uſe of: but we cannot think it was by theſe worthies intended, or ought to be made uſe of to the perpetuating of that ſupreme truſt and power in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of any, during their own pleaſures, or to the debarring of the people from their right and elections totally, now when thoſe dangers or exigencies were paſt and the affairs and ſafety of the Common-wealth would admit of ſuch a change.</p>
            <p>Having thus cleared our grounds and intentions (as we hope) from all ſcruples and miſunderſtandings in what follows, we ſhall proceed further to propoſe what we humbly deſire for the ſettling of our own and the Kingdomes rights and liberties, through the bleſſing of God to poſterity, and therefore up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the grounds promiſed, we further humbly deſire as followeth,</p>
            <p n="3">III. That ſome determinate period of time may be ſet for the continuance of this and future Parliaments, beyond which none ſhall continue, and upon which new Writs may of courſe iſſue out, and new elections ſucceſſively take place, according to the intent of the bill for Trienniall Parliaments.</p>
            <p>And herein we would not be miſunderſtood, to deſire a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or ſudden diſſolution of this Parliament, but onely (as is expreſt before) that ſome certain period may be ſet for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45897:7"/>
of it, ſo that it may not remain (as now) continuable for ever, or during the pleaſure of the preſent Members. And we ſhould deſire that the period to be now ſet for ending this Parliament may be ſuch as may give ſufficient time for proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what is wanting, and neceſſary to be paſſed in point of juſt reformation and further ſecuring the rights and liberties and ſettling the peace of the Kingdome, in order to which we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther humbly offer.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That ſecure proviſion may be made for the continuance of future Parliaments, ſo as they may not be adjournable or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvable at the Kings pleaſure, or any other wayes then by their own conſent during their reſpective periods: but all thoſe peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ods each Parliament to determine of courſe as before. This we deſire may be now provided for (if it may be) ſo as to put it out of all diſpute for future, though we think of right it ought not to have been otherwiſe before.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the preſent diſtribution of Elections for Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament Members is ſo very unequall, and the multitude of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes for decayed or inconſiderable Townes (whoſe intereſt in the Kingdome, would (in many) not exceed or (in others) not equall ordinary Villages) doth give too much and too evident opportunity for men of power to frame parties in Parliament to ſerve particular intereſt, and thereby the common intereſt of the whole is not ſo minded, or not ſo equally provided for, we therefore further deſire:</p>
            <p n="5">V. That ſome proviſion may be now made for ſuch diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Elections for future Parliaments as may ſtand with ſome rule of equality, or proportion as near as may be, to render the Parliament a more equall repreſentative of the whole, as (for inſtance) That all Counties or diviſions and parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (involving inconſiderable Towns) may have a number of Parliament men allowed to their choice, proportionably to the reſpective rates they bear in the common charges and burthens
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45897:7"/>
of the Kingdome, and not to have more; or ſome other ſuch like rule.</p>
            <p>And thus a firm foundation being laid in the authority and conſtitution of Parliament for the hopes at leaſt of common and equall right and freedome to our ſelves and all the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born people of this Land, we ſhall (for our parts) freely and chearfully commit our ſtock or ſhare of intereſt in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, into this common bottom of Parliament, and though it may (for our particulars) go ill with us in one voyage, yet we ſhall thus hope (if right be with us) to fare better in another.</p>
            <p>Theſe things we deſire may be provided for by bill or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament: to which the Royall Aſſent may be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And when his Majeſtie (in theſe things and what elſe ſhall be propoſed by the Parliament neceſſary for ſecuring the rights and liberties of the people, and for ſettling the Militia and peace of the Kingdome) ſhall have given his concurrence, to put them paſt diſpute; we ſhall then deſire that the rights of his Majeſtie and his poſterity may be conſidered of and ſettled in all things ſo far as may conſiſt with the right and freedome of the ſubject, and with the ſecurity of the ſame for future.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. We deſire, That the right and freedome of the people to repreſent to the Parliament by way of humble petition, their grievances, in ſuch things as cannot otherwiſe be remedied then by Parliament, may be cleared and vindicated, that all ſuch grievances of the people may be freely received, and admitted into conſideration, and put into an equitable and ſpeedy way to be heard, examined, and redreſſed, if they appear reall: and that in ſuch things, for which men have remedy by law, They may be freely left to the benefit of law and the regulated courſe of juſtice, without interruption or check from the Parliament, except in caſe of things done upon the exigency of warre, or for the ſervice and benefit of the Parliament and Kingdome in relation to the warre, or otherwiſe in due purſuance and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45897:8"/>
of Ordinances, or Orders of Parliament.</p>
            <p>More particularly (under this head) we cannot but deſire that all ſuch as are impriſoned for any pretended miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, may be put into a ſpeedy way for a juſt hearing and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and ſuch as ſhall appear to have been unjuſtly, and unduely impriſoned may (with their Liberty) have ſome reaſonable reparation according to their ſufferings, and the demerit of their oppreſſours,</p>
            <p n="7">VII. That the large power given to Committees, or Deputy Lievtenants, during the late times of war, and diſtraction may be ſpeedily taken into conſideration: That ſuch of thoſe powers as appear not neceſſary to be continued may be taken away, and ſuch of them as are neceſſary, may be put into a regulated way, and left to as little Arbitrarineſſe as the nature and neceſſity of the things wherein they are converſant will bear.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. We could wiſh that the Kingdome might both be righted, and publickly ſatisfied in point of Accounts for the vaſt ſummes that have been levied and paid, as alſo in divers other things wherein the common wealth may be conceived, to have been wronged or abuſed. But we are loth to preſſe any thing that may tend to lengthen out further diſputes, or conteſtations, but rather ſuch as may tend to a ſpeedy and Generall compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and quieting of mens minds in order to peace, for which purpoſe we further propoſe.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. That publick juſtice being firſt ſatisfied by ſome few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to poſterity out of the worſt of excepted perſons, and other delinquents, having paſt their Compoſitions, ſome courſe may be taken (by a generall act of oblivion; or otherwiſe) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſeeds of future War or Fewds either to the preſent Age, or Poſterity, may the better be taken away by eaſing that ſence of preſent, and ſatisfying thoſe fears of future ruine or undoing to perſons or families which may drive men into any deſperate wayes for ſelf preſervation and remedy, and by taking away the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45897:8"/>
private remembrances and diſtinctions of parties, as farre as may ſtand with ſafetie to the Rights and Liberties we have hitherto fought for.</p>
            <p>There are beſides theſe) many particular things which we could wiſh to be done, &amp; ſome to be undone; all in order ſtill to the ſame end of Common Right, Freedome, Peace, and Safety. But theſe propoſals aforegoing being the principall things we bottome and inſiſt upon, we ſhall as we have ſaid before for our parts acquieſce for other particulars in the wiſedome and juſtice of Parliament. And whereas it hath been ſuggeſted or ſuſpected that in our late or preſent proceedings our deſigne is to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Presbitery, or hinder the ſettlement thereof, and to have the Independent government ſet up: We do clearly diſclaim, and diſavow any ſuch deſign; we onely deſire that according to the Declarations promiſing a priviledge for tender Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there may be ſome effectuall courſe taken according to the intent thereof, and that ſuch who upon Conſcientious grounds may differ from the eſtabliſhed forms, may not for that be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from the common Rights, Liberties or Benefits belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally to all as men and Members of the Common-wealth, while they live ſoberly, honeſtly, inoffenſively to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, and peacefully and faithfully towards the State.</p>
            <p>We haue thus freely and clearly declared the depth and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of our hearts and deſires in order to the Rights, Liberties; and Peace of the Kingdome: wherein we appeal to all men whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſeek anything of advantage to our ſelves, or any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular party whatever to the prejudice of the whole, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the things we wiſh and ſeek do not equally concern and conduce to he good of others in common with our ſelves, according to the ſincerity of our deſires and intentions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as we have already found the concurrent ſence of the people in divers Counties by their Petitions to the Generall, expreſſing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45897:9"/>
their Reſentment of theſe things, and preſſing us to ſtand for the intereſt of the Kingdome therein, ſo we ſhall wiſh and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to find the unanimous concurrence of all others that are equally concerned with us in theſe things, and wiſh well to the Publick.</p>
            <p>And ſo (truſting in the mercy and goodneſſe of God to paſſe by and help any failings or infirmities of ours in the carriage or proceedings thereupon) we ſhall humbly caſt our ſelves and the buſineſſe upon his good pleaſure, depending onely on his preſence and bleſſing for an happy iſſue to the Peace and good of this poore Kingdome, in the accompliſhment whereof we deſire and hope that God will make you bleſſed Inſtruments.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45897:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
